Guide to the Speech Communication Department Records 1918-1996
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center
Speech Communication Department Records
1918-1996
1930-1975
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center Special Collections & University Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2165 Email: archives@oregonstate.edu Web: http://archives.library.oregonstate.edu
RG 181
Oregon State University. Dept. of Speech Communication.
1.25 cubic feet, including 3 photographs 2 boxes
7 microfilm reels
The Speech Communication Department Records document speech instruction at Oregon State University; speech, debate, and drama activities, especially during the 1920s through 1950s; and the activities of Earl W. Wells as a faculty member and department chair. Speech courses have been taught at Oregon State since its establishment in the late 1860s. The Speech Department was founded in 1920; Earl Wells was department chair from 1952 to 1962.
Historical Note:
Courses in elocution and speech have been taught at Oregon State University since its founding in the 1860s. During the 1890s, these were taught by the Department of Elocution and later by the Department of Public Speaking. The Department of Public Speaking and Dramatics was established in 1920, as the first Speech Department in Oregon, and grew quickly during the 1920s. Courses in "speech correction" were added in the mid-1920s. When higher education in Oregon was re-organized in the early 1930s, responsibility for speech degrees was transferred to the University of Oregon and several faculty moved to establish the program. However, the service department at Oregon State continued to offer courses in debating, extempore speaking, oratory, voice and diction, and radio speech and coordinated an extensive program of forensics and dramatic activities for students.
In 1965-1966, the Speech Department was one of the first departments to offer an undergraduate degree in the new School of Humanities and Social Sciences. In 1970, the department name was changed to Speech Communication.
C.B. (Charles Buren) Mitchell joined the faculty of Oregon Agricultural College in 1920 to head the new Department of Public Speaking and Dramatics. Earl W. Wells joined the department at about the same time (1921); he was instrumental in developing the forensics and public speaking program and coached orators who gained national prominence. Wells served as Speech Department Chair from 1952 until his retirement in 1962.
The Speech Communication Department Records document speech instruction at Oregon State as well as speech, debate, and drama activities. The Records include orations and speeches, correspondence, reports, organization records, course materials, committee minutes, a scrapbook, and several photographs. Of special note are records of the Oregon State chapter of Delta Sigma Rho, the national honorary society for students in speech communications, and an Institute on Advanced Communications Skills for junior and senior high school English and Speech teachers offered at OSU in summer 1967. The photographs are of the Institute's participants.
The collection includes substantial materials pertaining to forensics and dramatic activities at Oregon State including orations and speeches; annual reports for debate squads during the 1930s through 1950s; and annual activities reports detailing the number of students participating, results of forensics competitions, plays performed, and number of attendees at dramatic productions. Materials pertaining to speech pathology and the Department's clinical activities, especially during the 1930s-1950s, are included in the records.
A significant portion of the microfilmed records (Subgroup 1) consist of the correspondence of Earl W. Wells and document Wells' activities as a faculty member and department chair and his participation in national, regional, and state-wide professional organizations. Some of C.B. Mitchell's correspondence is also included.
Collection is open for research.
The Speech Communication Department Records are arranged in two subgroups: 1. Microfilmed Records, 1921-1969 and 2. Paper Records, 1918-1996. The microfilmed records consist of 9 series: I. Orations, 1921-1962; II. Speeches, 1923-1948; III. Debates, 1930-1956; IV. Army Specialized Training Program, 1943; V. Intercollegiate Forensic Association of Oregon, 1932-1962; VI. Activities Reports, 1928-1958; VII. Correspondence of Earl W. Wells, 1922-1967; VIII. Reader's File, 1931-1969; and IX. Report on the Forensic and Dramatic Activities at Oregon State College, 1938.
The paper records (Subgroup 2) are arranged in 10 series: I. Correspondence, 1952-1985; II. Delta Sigma Rho Records, 1920-1975; III. History of the Speech Department, 1918-1989; IV. Minutes of Speech Department Meetings, 1959-1970; V. National Defense Education Act (NDEA) Institute in English: Advanced Communication Skills, 1965-1968; VI. Committees, Organizations, and Conferences, 1933-1989; VII. Publication, 1940-1996; VIII. Reports, 1949-1974; IX. Scrapbook, 1964-1970; and X. Subject Files, 1948-1961.
The records were transferred to the University Archives in several accessions from 1970 through 2005.
Additions to the collection are expected.
The Speech Department Photographs (P 088) include images of students who participated in speech and debate activities, faculty, and facilities. The Effie L. Wagner Scrapbook of the Women's Debate Tour documents the 1928 Women's Debate Tour of several colleges and universities in the western United States. The Special Collections & Archives Research Center's holdings also include the Drama, Debate, and Oration Scrapbooks for 1920-1963. Two compilations of Oregon State's achievements in intercollegiate oratorical competition for 1920-1945 by Earl W. Wells are available in the Special Collections & Archives Research Center's Vault Collection. Extensive documentation of theater and dramatics programs are available in the University Theater Records (RG 180), University Theater Photographs (P 112), and C.B. Mitchell University Theater Scrapbooks. General information about the Speech Department is available in the Memorabilia Collection.
Mitchell, C. B. (Charles Buren), 1886-1955.; Wells, Earl W. (Earl William), b. 1898.
Oregon Agricultural College--Students.; Oregon State College--Students.; Oregon State University--Students.; Delta Sigma Rho.; Delta Sigma Rho. Oregon State College Chapter.; Oregon State Agricultural College. Dept. of Public Speaking and Dramatics.; Oregon State College. Dept. of Speech.; Oregon State University. Dept. of Speech.
College and school drama, American--Oregon--Corvallis.; College orations--Oregon State College.; Debates and debating--Oregon--Corvallis.; Drama--Study and teaching--Oregon--Corvallis.; Forensics (Public speaking); Oratory--Societies, etc.; Oratory--Study and teaching--Oregon.; Speech--Study and teaching--Oregon.; Speech therapy--Oregon--Corvallis.; Student activities--Oregon--Corvallis.; Women--Oregon--Corvallis.
Scrapbooks.; Photographic prints.
Colleges and Universities; Performing Arts; Student Life; Women; Oregon; Corvallis; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Microfilmed Records, 1921-1969; Subgroup 1
  Subgroup 1 consists of microfilmed Speech Department records documenting speech, debate, and drama activities; the work of Earl. W. Wells as faculty member and department chair; and department administration. The records are primarily for the 1930s thru 1950s and include correspondence, reports, speeches, and orations.
  - Orations, 1921-1962; Series I
    Series I consists of the texts of orations given at contests by Oregon State students as well as students from other regional colleges and universities.
    - 1921-1930, 1 (Reel 1)
    - 1931-1932, 2 (Reel 1)
    - 1932-1933, 3 (Reel 1)
    - 1933-1934, 4 (Reel 1)
    - 1934-1935, 5 (Reel 1)
    - 1935-1936, 6 (Reel 1)
    - 1936-1937, 7 (Reel 1)
    - 1937-1938, 8 (Reel 1-2)
    - 1938-1939, 9 (Reel 2)
    - 1939-1940, 10 (Reel 2)
    - 1940-1941, 11 (Reel 2)
    - 1941-1942, 12 (Reel 2)
    - 1942-1943, 13 (Reel 2)
    - 1943-1944, 14 (Reel 2)
    - 1944-1945, 15 (Reel 2)
    - 1945-1946, 16 (Reel 2)
    - 1946-1947, 17 (Reel 2)
    - 1947-1948, 18 (Reel 2)
    - 1948-1949, 19 (Reel 2)
    - 1949-1950, 20 (Reel 2)
    - 1950-1951, 21 (Reel 2-3)
    - 1951-1952, 22 (Reel 3)
    - 1952-1953, 23 (Reel 3)
    - 1955-1956, 24 (Reel 3)
    - 1956-1957, 25 (Reel 3)
    - 1957-1958, 26 (Reel 3)
    - 1958-1959, 27 (Reel 3)
    - 1959-1960, 28 (Reel 3)
    - 1960-1961, 29 (Reel 3)
    - 1961-1962, 30 (Reel 3-4)
    - Oratorical Contest Speeches, 1931-1948; 31 (Reel 4)
  - Speeches, 1923-1948; Series II
    Series II consists of speeches presented by Oregon State students at forensics competitions.
    - Extempore Speeches, 1923-1938
      - 1923-1931, 32 (Reel 4)
      - 1931-1932, 33 (Reel 4)
      - 1932-1933, 34 (Reel 4)
      - 1933-1934, 35 (Reel 4)
      - 1934-1935, 36 (Reel 4)
      - 1935-1936, 37 (Reel 4)
      - 1936-1937, 38 (Reel 4)
      - 1936-1937, 38 (Reel 4)
      - 1937-1938, 39 (Reel 4)
    - After-Dinner Speeches, 1938-1948
      - 1938-1939, 40 (Reel 4)
      - 1939-1940, 41 (Reel 4)
      - 1940-1941, 42 (Reel 4)
      - 1941-1942, 43 (Reel 4)
      - 1942-1943, 44 (Reel 4)
      - 1943-1944, 45 (Reel 4)
      - 1944-1945, 46 (Reel 4)
      - 1945-1946, 47 (Reel 4)
      - 1946-1947, 48 (Reel 4)
      - 1947-1948, 49 (Reel 4)
    - Auto Accident Prevention Contest, 1935; 50 (Reel 4)
      Contest for freshmen extempore speaking.
  - Debates, 1930-1956; Series III
    Series III includes reports of each debating season for the 1930s through mid 1950s documenting the members of the men's and women's debate squads, the number of debates each squad participated in, and the number of debates that were won by Oregon State squads. The series also includes information about the participation of Oregon State squads in the annual West Point Debates.
    - Season Reports for Debate Squads, 1930-1956; 51 (Reel 4)
    - Radio Debates, 1937; 52 (Reel 4)
    - West Point Debates, 1947-1951; 53 (Reel 4)
  - Army Specialized Training Program, 1943; Series IV
    Series IV consists of syllabi, correspondence, and related materials pertaining to speech training in AST 111.
    - General, 54 (Reel 4)
  - Intercollegiate Forensic Association of Oregon, 1932-1962; Series V
    Series V consists of documents of the Intercollegiate Forensic Association of Oregon, which included representatives from colleges and universities throughout the state. The Association sponsored forensics contests and activities.
    - Directories, Bulletins, and Minutes, 55 (Reel 4)
  - Activities Reports, 1928-1958; Series VI
    Series VI consists of annual reports of dramatics and forensics activities at Oregon State, including the number of participating students; results of forensics competitions; plays performed; and number of attendees at dramatic productions.
    - 1928-1929, 56 (Reel 4)
    - 1929-1930, 57 (Reel 4)
    - 1930-1931, 58 (Reel 4)
    - 1931-1932, 59 (Reel 4)
    - 1932-1933, 60 (Reel 4)
    - 1934-1935, 61 (Reel 4)
    - 1935-1936, 62 (Reel 4)
    - 1936-1937, 63 (Reel 4)
    - 1937-1938, 64 (Reel 4)
    - 1938-1939, 65 (Reel 4)
    - 1939-1940, 66 (Reel 4)
    - 1940-1941, 67 (Reel 4)
    - 1941-1942, 68 (Reel 4)
    - 1942-1943, 69 (Reel 4)
    - 1943-1944, 70 (Reel 4)
    - 1944-1945, 71 (Reel 4)
    - 1945-1946, 72 (Reel 4)
    - 1946-1947, 73 (Reel 4)
    - 1947-1948, 74 (Reel 4)
    - 1948-1949, 75 (Reel 4)
    - 1949-1950, 76 (Reel 4)
    - 1950-1951, 77 (Reel 4)
    - 1951-1952, 78 (Reel 4)
    - 1952-1953, 79 (Reel 4)
    - 1953-1954, 80 (Reel 4)
    - 1954-1955, 81 (Reel 4-5)
    - 1955-1956, 82 (Reel 5)
    - 1956-1957, 83 (Reel 5)
    - 1957-1958, 84 (Reel 5)
  - Correspondence of Earl W. Wells, 1922-1967; Series VII
    Series VII consists of correspondence received and sent by Earl W. Wells in his role as a Speech Department faculty member as well as department chair. The series also includes some personal correspondence for Wells, such as that for the Corvallis Rose Society.
    - Miscellaneous Current, 1961-1962; 85 (Reel 5)
    - Miscellaneous Past, 1922-1961
      - Volume I, 1922-1933; 86 (Reel 5)
      - Volume II, 1935-1940; 87 (Reel 5)
      - Volume III, 1940-1950; 88 (Reel 5)
      - Volume IV, 1950-1961; 89 (Reel 5)
    - Radio and Television, 1954-1958; 90 (Reel 5)
    - Publishing Companies, 1927-1937; 91 (Reel 5)
    - NDEA Brochure Copy, 1966-1967; 92 (Reel 5)
    - Speech Faculty, 1954-1962
      - 1954-1955, 93 (Reel 5)
      - 1955-1956, 94 (Reel 5)
      - 1956-1957, 95 (Reel 5)
      - 1957-1958, 96 (Reel 5)
      - 1958-1959, 97 (Reel 5)
      - 1959-1960, 98 (Reel 5)
      - 1961-1962, 99 (Reel 5)
    - President Jensen, 1962; 100 (Reel 5)
    - C.B. Mitchell's Personal Correspondence, 1925-1943; 101 (Reel 5)
    - Colby - Dean of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1952-1961
      - 1952-1953, 102 (Reel 5)
      - 1953-1954, 103 (Reel 5)
      - 1954-1955, 104 (Reel 5)
      - 1955-1956, 105 (Reel 5)
      - 1956-1957, 106 (Reel 5)
      - 1957-1958, 107 (Reel 5)
      - 1958-1959, 108 (Reel 5)
      - 1959-1960, 109 (Reel 5)
      - 1960-1961, 110 (Reel 5)
    - Equipment - General, 1956-1961; 111 (Reel 5)
    - Speech Aptitude and Proficiency Test, 1948-1952; 112 (Reel 5)
    - Speech Correction Extension Vol. I, 1927-1950; 113 (Reel 5)
    - Western Speech Association Vol. III, 1950-1960; 114 (Reel 5)
    - American Association of University Professors, 1946-1962; 115 (Reel 5)
    - American Forensic Association, 1958-1961; 116 (Reel 5)
    - American Red Cross, 1936-1947; 117 (Reel 5)
    - American Speech and Hearing Association, 1936-1963; 118 (Reel 5)
    - Century Club, 1936-1957; 119 (Reel 5)
    - Committee on Disaster Preparedness and Relief, 1936-1946; 120 (Reel 5)
    - Clinical Staff, 1948-1955; 121 (Reel 5)
    - Committee on Scholarship, 1938-1940; 122 (Reel 5)
    - Committee on Teacher Selection, 1940-1948; 123 (Reel 5)
    - Corvallis Boy Scouts, 1936-1938; 124 (Reel 5)
    - Corvallis Camp Fire Girls, 1937-1941; 125 (Reel 5)
    - Corvallis Rose Society, 1958-1960; 126 (Reel 5)
    - Corvallis Summer Recreation and Educational Program, 1935-1937; 127 (Reel 5)
    - Delta Sigma Rho
      - Volume I, 1926-1949; 128 (Reel 5-6)
      - Volume II, 1951-1955; 129 (Reel 6)
      - Volume III, 1955-1961; 130 (Reel 6)
    - Democratic Party, 1955-1960; 131 (Reel 1)
    - Educational Activities Committee, 1951-1955; 132 (Reel 6)
    - Faculty Council, 1957-1961; 133 (Reel 6)
    - Future Farmers of America, 1936-1960; 134 (Reel 6)
    - Franklin Parent - Teachers Association, 1931-1932; 135 (Reel 6)
    - Faculty Men's Club, 1957-1962; 136 (Reel 6)
    - Graduate Division, 1960; 137 (Reel 6)
    - Inland Empire Education Association, 1928-1930; 138 (Reel 6)
    - Intercollegiate Forensic Association of Oregon, 1931-1961; 139 (Reel 6)
    - Liberal Arts Division, 1949-1962; 140 (Reel 6)
    - Order of the Spoon, 1929-1939; 141 (Reel 6)
    - Oregon High School Extempore Speaking and Interpretation Contests, 1925-1932; 142 (Reel 6)
    - Oregon High School Speech League, 1942-1951; 143 (Reel 6)
    - Oregon Speech and Hearing Association, 1949-1962; 144 (Reel 6)
    - Oregon Speech Association, 1931-1950; 145 (Reel 6)
  - Reader's File, 1931-1969; Series VIII
    Series VIII consists of department correspondence arranged as reader's files. The correspondence documents the administration of the department, primarily during the 1950s and 1960s.
    - Bulletins: Business Office, 1956-1957; 146 (Reel 6)
    - Business Office, 1956-1960
      - 1956-1959, 147 (Reel 6)
      - 1959-1960, 148 (Reel 6)
    - Colby - Dean of Liberal Arts, 1946-1952
      - 1946-1950, 149 (Reel 6)
      - 1950-1951, 150 (Reel 6)
      - 1951-1952, 151 (Reel 6)
    - Faculty - Other, 1950-1959
      - 1950-1951, 152 (Reel 6)
      - 1951-1952, 153 (Reel 6)
      - 1953-1954, 154 (Reel 6)
      - 1954-1955, 155 (Reel 6)
      - 1955-1956, 156 (Reel 6)
      - 1958-1959, 157 (Reel 6)
    - Lemon - Dean of Administration, 1951-1954
      - 1951-1952, 158 (Reel 6)
      - 1953-1954, 159 (Reel 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1948-1959
      - 1948-1950, 160 (Reel 6)
      - 1951-1952, 161 (Reel 6)
      - 1952-1953, 162 (Reel 6)
      - 1952-1953, 162 (Reel 6)
      - 1954-1955, 163 (Reel 6)
      - 1955-1956, 164 (Reel 6)
      - 1958-1959, 165 (Reel 6)
    - Self Evaluation Report II, circa 1960; 166 (Reel 6)
    - Other Institutions, 1951-1952; 167 (Reel 6)
    - Physical Plant, 1950-1953; 168 (Reel 6)
    - President Strand, 1931-1952
      - 1931-1951, 169 (Reel 6)
      - 1951-1952, 170 (Reel 6)
    - Zeran - Dean of Education, 1952-1961
      - 1952, 171 (Reel 6)
      - 1961, 172 (Reel 6)
    - Chronological Reader's File, 1963-1969
      - September 1963, 173 (Reel 6)
      - October 1963, 174 (Reel 6)
      - November 1963, 175 (Reel 6)
      - December 1963, 176 (Reel 6)
      - January 1964, 177 (Reel 6)
      - February 1964, 178 (Reel 6)
      - March 1964, 179 (Reel 6)
      - April 1964, 180 (Reel 6)
      - May 1964, 181 (Reel 6)
      - June 1964, 182 (Reel 6)
      - July 1964, 183 (Reel 6)
      - August 1964, 184 (Reel 6)
      - September - October 1964, 185 (Reel 6)
      - November 1964, 186 (Reel 6)
      - December 1964, 187 (Reel 6)
      - January 1965, 188 (Reel 6)
      - February 1965, 189 (Reel 6)
      - March 1965, 190 (Reel 6)
      - April 1965, 191 (Reel 6)
      - May 1965, 192 (Reel 6)
      - June 1965, 193 (Reel 6)
      - July 1965, 194 (Reel 6)
      - August 1965, 195 (Reel 6)
      - September 1965, 196 (Reel 6)
      - October 1965, 197 (Reel 6)
      - November 1965, 198 (Reel 6)
      - December 1965, 199 (Reel 6)
      - January 1966, 200 (Reel 6)
      - February 1966, 201 (Reel 6)
      - March 1966, 202 (Reel 6)
      - April 1966, 203 (Reel 6)
      - May 1966, 204 (Reel 6)
      - June 1966, 205 (Reel 6)
      - September 1966, 206 (Reel 6)
      - October 1966, 207 (Reel 6)
      - December 1966, 208 (Reel 6)
      - January 1967, 209 (Reel 6)
      - February 1967, 210 (Reel 6)
      - March 1967, 211 (Reel 6)
      - April 1967, 212 (Reel 6)
      - May 1967, 213 (Reel 6)
      - June 1967, 214 (Reel 6)
      - July 1967, 215 (Reel 6)
      - August 1967, 216 (Reel 6)
      - September 1967, 217 (Reel 6)
      - October 1967, 218 (Reel 6)
      - November 1967, 219 (Reel 6)
      - December 1967, 220 (Reel 6-7)
      - January 1968, 221 (Reel 7)
      - February 1968, 222 (Reel 7)
      - March 1968, 223 (Reel 7)
      - April 1968, 224 (Reel 7)
      - May 1968, 225 (Reel 7)
      - June 1968, 226 (Reel 7)
      - July 1968, 227 (Reel 7)
      - August 1968, 228 (Reel 7)
      - September 1968, 229 (Reel 7)
      - October 1968, 230 (Reel 7)
      - November 1968, 231 (Reel 7)
      - December 1968, 232 (Reel 7)
      - January 1969, 233 (Reel 7)
      - February 1969, 234 (Reel 7)
      - March 1969, 235 (Reel 7)
      - April 1969, 236 (Reel 7)
      - May 1969, 237 (Reel 7)
      - June 1969, 238 (Reel 7)
      - December 1969, 239 (Reel 7)
  - Report on the Forensic and Dramatic Activities at Oregon State College, 1938; Series IX
    Series IX consists of a report documenting the speech, debate, and drama activities of the department during the 1920s and 1930s.
    - Report on the Forensic and Dramatic Activities at Oregon State College since the Establishment of the Department of Speech, Fall 1920 to Spring 1938, 240 (Reel 7)
- Paper Records, 1918-1996; Subgroup 2
  Subgroup 2 consists of Speech Communication Department Records in paper form documenting the curriculum, policies and procedures, faculty, and student activities of the department. Of special note are records of Delta Sigma Rho, the national honorary society for students in speech communications, and the National Defense Education Act (NDEA) Institute in English on Advance Communications Skills held at Oregon State in 1967.
  - Correspondence, 1952-1985; Series I
    Series I consists of correspondence received and sent from the department and documents the policies and procedures of the department, facilities, faculty, and courses. The fall letter to the Speeech Department from Earl W. Wells, Department Chair, introduces new and returning faculty, summarizes department policies and procedures, and lists advising responsibilities.
    - Fall letter to members of Speech Department, 1952-1961 (Box 1)
    - Policy and Historical, 1955-1967 (Box 1)
    - General Speech Department Correspondence, 1968-1985 (Box 1)
  - Delta Sigma Rho Records, 1920-1975; Series II
    Series II consists of records of the Oregon State University chapter of Delta Sigma Rho, the national honorary society for students in speech communications. The records include constitutions, correspondence, membership lists, initiation rituals, and financial records.
    - Account ledger and finances, 1931-1947 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1920-1934 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1972 (Box 1)
    - Initiation rituals, 1941-1967 (Box 1)
    - Membership lists, 1929-1953 (Box 1)
    - Procedures and constitutions, 1966-1975 (Box 1)
    - Sample membership cards, 1932-1953 (Box 1)
  - History of the Speech Department, 1918-1989; Series III
    Series III consists of research notes on the history of the department compiled by Thurston Doler. The notes include correspondence as well as photocopies from the Beaver yearbook. Several short essays on the history of the Speech Department are also part of the series.
    - Research notes, 1918-1989 (Box 1)
    - Essays, 1966-1982 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Speech Department Meetings, 1959-1970; Series IV
    Series IV consists of minutes of department meetings and compilations of the minutes of the Executive Committee and the Department Staff. These compilations consists of copies of the minutes that have been clipped and re-assembled by topic. A list of topics is in the front of the first folder for each. The Executive Committee minutes include materials relevant to the National Defense Education Act (NDEA) Institute at OSU in 1967.
    - Department meeting, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Executive committee, 1964-1970; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Staff meetings, 1964-1970; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - National Defense Education Act (NDEA) Institute in English: Advanced Communication Skills, 1965-1968; Series V
    Series V consists of the records of an National Defence Education Act (NDEA) Institute in English on Advance Communication Skills offered at Oregon State University. The 8-week course, from June 26 through August 18, 1967, was attended by 32 junior and senior high school English and Speech teachers. The program focussed on the multiple and interdisciplinary aspects of human communication skills. The records include the proposal, plan of operation, and final report; course materials; correspondence; brochures and clippings; lists of participants; and a group photograph of the participants.
    - Correspondence, 1966-1967
      - Dr. Milton Valentine's NDEA Institute correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
      - Exhibit requests, 1967 (Box 1)
      - General correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
      - Participant and alternate rejection letters, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Course Materials, 1965-1967
      - Psychology of Reading, undated (Box 1)
      - Various courses, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - Finances, 1966-1968
      - 4 Column Book, 1967 (Box 1)
      - Dr. Valentine's expenditure receipts and related correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
      - Stipend information and related correspondence, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings and brochures, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Participant lists, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Participant group photograph, 1967; 2 prints and 1 120 negative (Box 1)